<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Choice remarks on the most observable actions performed by Lewis the XIV, present king in France</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 53 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A32875</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C3919</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R29217</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">10861624</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 10861624</idno>
            <idno type="VID">46139</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A32875)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 46139)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1419:37)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Choice remarks on the most observable actions performed by Lewis the XIV, present king in France</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>18 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Richard Janeway,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Louis --  XIV, --  King of France, 1638-1715.</term>
               <term>France --  History --  Louis XIV, 1643-1715.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:46139:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:46139:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Choice Remarks,</hi> On the moſt Obſervable ACTIONS Performed by Lewis the XIV. PRESENT KING IN FRANCE.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Richard Janeway,</hi> in <hi>Queenſ-Head-Ally,</hi> in <hi>Pater-Noſter Row.</hi> In the Year 1681.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:46139:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:46139:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Choice Remarks</hi> On the moſt obſervable Actions, performed by <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIV. Preſent King in <hi>France.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Ewis</hi> the 13th. by his laſt Will and Teſtament, ordained that the Queen his Wife ſhould have the Government and Charge of the Perſon of King <hi>Lewis</hi> the 14th. his Son, during his Mino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and the Regency of the Kingdom. This young Prince was not much advanced in the fifth year of his Age ere he began to triumph over his Enemies, through the ſucceſsful Conduct of the Duke <hi>D'Anguien</hi> at the memorable Battel of <hi>Rocroy,</hi> and the gaining of <hi>Thionvillle,</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a Siege of twenty-two days.</p>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>Orleans</hi> the Kings Uncle, Lieutenant-General of the Kingdom, added to his Victories the taking of <hi>Graveline,</hi> where <hi>Marſhal de Gaſſion</hi> gave moſt ſignal Proofs of his Vallor. Thus <hi>Luxemburgh,</hi> being taught that an Infant King, might be Victorious, <hi>Germany</hi> was now to learn the ſame Leſſon. The Duke of <hi>Anguien</hi> advances to the Banks of the <hi>Rhine,</hi> Attacks the <hi>Bavarian</hi> Army, and three times defeats them. He ſurrounds and takes <hi>Philipsburgh,</hi> for which reaſon <hi>Wormes</hi> would not diſpute with him any longer for her Liberty, no more then <hi>Mayence,</hi> beſides a great number of other Cities that gloried in opening their Gates to the Conquerer. The retaking of <hi>Leri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da</hi> in ſome meaſure counterballanc'd ſo many great advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. But the next year we continued the Progreſs of our Conqueſts in <hi>Lorraine</hi> by the taking <hi>La Mothe,</hi> where the <hi>Sieur Magalotti</hi> who commanded for the King, received his deaths wound; and in <hi>Catalogna</hi> under the conduct of the <hi>Count</hi> of <hi>Harcourt,</hi> who was received into <hi>Barcellona</hi> with applauſe and Acclamation. He defeated the <hi>Spaniards</hi> at the Battel of <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orens,</hi> in which the Enemy loſt between five and ſix thouſand Men. After that he took the City of <hi>Balagnier,</hi> ſome Months after that, the Count of <hi>Pleſſis-Praſlin,</hi> had alſo in <hi>Rouſſillon</hi> reduced <hi>Roſes</hi> to his Majeſties obedience.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:46139:3"/>
            <p>During ſo many brave exploits the <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Orleans</hi> was was not idle in <hi>Flanders,</hi> where he took by force the Cities of <hi>Pourbourk, Links, Lans, Bethune, Liters, St. Venant, Arenantieres, Menene,</hi> and other places in that Province. Nor was the <hi>Duked Anguien</hi> leſs proſperous in <hi>Germany,</hi> where that young Prince gave Battel to the Imperialiſts and <hi>Bavarians,</hi> whom he defeated near to <hi>Nortlingen,</hi> with the loſs of their <hi>General Mercy,</hi> who was killed with a Musket ſhot; and their Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral <hi>Gleen,</hi> who was taken Priſoner, the all afterwards ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changed for Marſhal <hi>Grammont,</hi> who fell into the Enemies hands at the beginning of the Fight. Inſomuch, that by that Victory, the <hi>Imperialiſts</hi> and <hi>Bavarians</hi> were very much weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ened, and conſtrained to retreat out of our way for their Oecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, which gave us opportunity to take <hi>Treves,</hi> and ſettle the Elector of that place.</p>
            <p>1645. This year concluded happily with the Marriage of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ladiſlaus,</hi> King of <hi>Poland,</hi> with the Princeſs <hi>Louiſe Maria de Gonzaga of Mantua,</hi> Daughter of <hi>Charles</hi> Duke of <hi>Gonzaga, Cleves, Mantua</hi> and <hi>Nevers</hi> deceaſed.</p>
            <p>So many glorious ſucceſſes happening to our Nation begat in the minds of the Spaniard that Stomackful deſpight which was the occaſion of much Diviſion at <hi>Rome.</hi> For as that City is the place where the Animoſity between the French and Spaniard moſt publickly appears, it ſoon fell out, that a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference aroſe between Prince <hi>Cardinal d' Eſte,</hi> Protector of <hi>France,</hi> and the Admiral of <hi>Caſtile,</hi> Embaſſador of Obedience from the moſt Catholick-King in that Court: and this the more eaſily in regard that the Spaniſh-Faction believed it ſelf to be the ſtrongeſt both in Number, and by reaſon of the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinity of <hi>Naples.</hi> But the <hi>Spaniards</hi> forgat that it never was the Cuſtome of the <hi>French</hi> to number their Enemies; howe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, that they always bring their Deſigns to paſs, when they find the Honour of their Prince concern'd. So that this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute was gloriouſly decided for the French, in regard the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lucky diſhonour redounded to the Spaniards, to have made a great noiſe, vaſt preparations, but to have given very little proof of their Courage.</p>
            <p>1646. This year produced Prodigies in <hi>Flanders,</hi> ſuch as were the taking of <hi>Lancy, Courtroy, Bergues,</hi> and <hi>Mardike,</hi> the retaking of which, was not a little fatal to <hi>France,</hi> through the loſs of ſo many brave Gentlemen. The Count of <hi>Fois</hi> was one of thoſe <hi>Hero</hi>'s that encountered the Danger, being the firſt that entered the Trench, where nothing could reſiſt his Courage; at length wearied as he was, while he was Charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Enemy a ſecond time, he was ſhot in the ſide with a Musket-Bullet, of which Wound he dyed ſoon after. Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs this Conſolation reſted with that Generous Prince in his Misfortune, that he had followed the ſteps of the moſt Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrious
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:46139:3"/>of his Predeceſſors, ending his days with a Death like that of the Famous <hi>Gaſton de Fois,</hi> whoſe Illuſtrious Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons he had ſo ſtrictly imitated. The Duke of <hi>Nemours</hi> in that Aſſault received a Wound in the Knee, the Prince of <hi>Marcellac</hi> in the Shoulder. But the Count of <hi>Rocheguion,</hi> and the <hi>Chevalier de Fieſque</hi> were ſo unfortunate as to looſe their Lives upon the ſpot.</p>
            <p>The taking of <hi>Dunkirk</hi> recomforted the Duke of <hi>Anguien</hi> for them is fortune of his moſt intimate Confidents. After which he underſtood with no ſmall Joy, that the defeat of the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon of <hi>Baſſee,</hi> was the Act of the <hi>Marſhal de Melleray,,</hi> who was ordered by his Majeſty to paſs into <hi>Piedmont</hi> to joyn with the Marſhal <hi>de Preſſis-Praſlin.</hi> Thoſe two Generals, after they had recruited our Naval-Forces, took ſoon after <hi>Piombino,</hi> and <hi>Porto Longone,</hi> and by ſuch noble Exploits they made us eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly forget the misfortune of the Siege of <hi>Orbitello.</hi> We were alſo thereby the leſs ſenſible of the loſs of <hi>Armentier</hi> and <hi>Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drecies,</hi> of which Arch-Duke <hi>Leopold,</hi> made himſelf Maſter in the year 1647. Which was a year remarkable for variety of Accidents. The Spaniſh Navy was defeated by the French, upon the Sea of <hi>Genoa,</hi> in ſight of <hi>Naples,</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Breze,</hi> who commanded the Fleet, was killed with a Cannon-Shot. The Duke of <hi>Anguien,</hi> now Prince of <hi>Conde,</hi> by the deceaſe of <hi>Lewis</hi> of <hi>Bourbon</hi> his Father, was conſtrained to raiſe the Siege of <hi>Lerida.</hi> The Marſhal <hi>de Gaſſion</hi> was ſlain before the City of <hi>Lens.</hi> But the revolt of the Kingdom of <hi>Naples,</hi> was a more then ordinary Prank of Fortune. Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs the Duke of <hi>Gueſe</hi> did not meet with thoſe advantages, there, with which he flattered himſelf; by reaſon that through the Treachery of certain <hi>Neapolitans</hi> he fell unforrtunately in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the hands of the <hi>Spaniayds,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If at the beginning of the year 1648. the French, as well as the Sweads had all the advantages they could deſire in <hi>Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,</hi> by reaſon of the defeat of the <hi>Imperialiſts</hi> and <hi>Bavarians,</hi> of which there were ſlain and taken Priſoners, about nine or ten thouſand, of which number alſo was their General <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lander;</hi> our affairs went on with no leſs ſucceſsful proſperity in <hi>Catalogna,</hi> where Marſhal <hi>Shomburgh</hi> having conſtrained the <hi>Spaniards</hi> to Retreat from the Siege of <hi>Flix,</hi> took in the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Tortoſa,</hi> after he had lain before it ſome Months. But in <hi>Flanders,</hi> Fortunegiving ſome kind of check to Balance the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity of the Kings Forces, made us looſe <hi>Courtray,</hi> to give <hi>Ipre</hi> into our poſſeſſion. After which ſucceſs, the Spaniards be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving us too weak to oppoſe them, by reaſon of our loſſes ſuſtained in the laſt Siege, forced us to give them Battel near to <hi>Lens,</hi> wherein they were wholly defeated with the loſs of eight thouſand Men, though their Army exceeded ours a third part in number.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:46139:4"/>
            <p>This Victory, which could not chooſe but be the Subject of the General joy of <hi>France,</hi> was the occaſion of a World of Miſery, whereto ſhe was afterwards reduced. While they were returning thanks to God for this Victory in the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedral Church of <hi>Paris,</hi> in another place they were provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Priſons for the <hi>Sieurs de Brouſſel,</hi> Counſellor in the Grand Chamber, <hi>Blanc-Menel &amp; Charton,</hi> Preſidents of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament. The Confinement of theſe three perſons cauſed moſt horrid diſorders in <hi>Paris,</hi> where you might have ſeen in a moment the Chains faſtened, the Barricados put up, and all the People in Arms, which nevertheleſs they ſoon laid down, after that the Queen, at the Prayer of the Parliament had wiſely granted them the Liberty of thoſe three Senators. The Calm laſted till the Kings leaving the City, who was carried out of <hi>Paris</hi> upon the fifth or ſixth at Night; which put the Burgeſſes to take Arms again. But the Parliament apprehenſive of the Miſchiefs that might happen by reaſon of theſe miſunderſtandings, ſent a conſiderable part of their Members to St. <hi>Germans,</hi> where his Majeſty lay, who put forth the Declaration of the Month of <hi>March,</hi> by which the Souldiers being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded from <hi>Paris,</hi> to the Frontiers, where the <hi>Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards</hi> were taking their advantages of their regaining <hi>Ipre,</hi> the Face of things began to alter ſo, that there was great hopes of a new repoſe and quiet upon the Return of the King.</p>
            <p>But all our hopes were quite daſhed, when we beheld the Princes of <hi>Conde</hi> and <hi>Longuevile</hi> in <hi>Bois de</hi> of <hi>Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cennes, Guien</hi> and <hi>Provence</hi> all in an uproare, becauſe of their Governors, whoſe behaviour and management was inſupportable to the people of thoſe two Provinces. The Kings preſence was requiſite to reduce <hi>Bourdeaux</hi> to obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience; Therefore his Majeſty marched thither, and having forced his entrance after ſome Reſiſtance, he conſtrained the Heads of the adverſe Party to retire.</p>
            <p>All the Conqueſts of Arch-Duke <hi>Leopold,</hi> during theſe Diviſions in <hi>France,</hi> were bounded by the taking of <hi>Mouzon</hi> and <hi>Rethel;</hi> of which laſt place he was not long Maſter, as being afterwards regained in the Month of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember by our Army wherein was Cardinal <hi>Mazarine</hi> in perſon.</p>
            <p>The Parliament judging that the Liberty of the Princes might be a means to reſtore tranquility to the Kingdom, as well as the retirement of Cardinal <hi>Mazarine,</hi> went in a Body to Petition the King for the Liberty of thoſe Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:46139:4"/>Priſoners, and ſometime after made their humble Remonſtrances to his Majeſty, for the Removal of the Cardinal from the Management of Publick Affairs, to take away all pretence and Colour of a Civil-War.</p>
            <p>Some few days after the Cardinal was retired, the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces being ſet at Liberty, arrived at <hi>Paris,</hi> where they were received with a moſt incredible Joy, out of a hope which all Men had conceived, that their return would pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent all thoſe misfortunes which ſeemed to threaten us. But ſo far we were from beholding that good Fortune with which we flattered our ſelves, and which the Majo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the King, the ſolemnities of which, were performed with an extraordinary Pomp, was in all probability moſt likely to ſettle, that we were ſenſible of new miſeries, apprehenſive of renewing Calamities. For the Prince of <hi>Conde</hi> out of his diſtruſt, not finding it requiſite to cloſe with the Court, retired to his New Government of <hi>Guien,</hi> whither being purſued by the Army, and more then that by the preſence of the Kings perſon, he treated with <hi>Spain,</hi> makes a powerful party in <hi>Gaſconie,</hi> and from thence, as Cardinal <hi>Mazarine</hi> was reentred <hi>France</hi> he return'd to <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris,</hi> where the Duke of <hi>Orleans</hi> joyned with him againſt the Cardinal their Common Enemy.</p>
            <p>In the mean time, the King beſieges <hi>Eſtampes,</hi> wherein the Army of the Princes was encloſed; but the event did not prove ſo advantagious to the King, who was oblig'd to retire with his Army and to ſurround <hi>Paris,</hi> where during the whole remainder of the Campaign, ſeveral Skirmiſhes happened on both ſides upon the Arrival of the <hi>Lorrainers,</hi> who ſhunned however, as much as in them lay, a general Battel; yet could not avoid a ſmart en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter in the Suburbs of St. <hi>Anthony,</hi> where were ſlain on both ſides above a thouſand Men upon the place, and where the Prince of <hi>Conde</hi> ſhewed all the Conduct and Bravery that could be expected from a valiant Captain, and yet if <hi>Madamoiſelle</hi> had not cauſed the Gate of the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to be opened, and diſcharged ſome pieces of Canon from the <hi>Baſtille,</hi> the Princes Army had been utterly Routed.</p>
            <p>But two days after, the diſorder happened to be ſo great in <hi>Paris,</hi> that the People were forced to weare Straw to ſhew the averſion which they had againſt the Cardinal, which occaſioned ſoon after the burning of the Gate of the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:46139:5"/>City Common-Hall where, to unite the City with the Parliament, three hundred noted Burgeſſes were Aſſembled, of whom the Mutineers, out of a Deſign to deſtroy them all, Murdered the <hi>Sieur Le Grat,</hi> Maſter of the Requeſts, <hi>de Janvry,</hi> Counſellor in Parliament, <hi>Myron,</hi> Maſter of the Accompts, and ſeveral others as they came out of the Aſſembly. The <hi>Sieur Doujat,</hi> Counſeller of the great Chamber, and ſome other Perſons of quality had run the ſame Fortune, had they not found a way by diſguiſing themſelves to Slip unknown through the Mutineers by the favour of the Night, who at length came to that Degree of Inſolence, as to force the Prieſtly and Religious Orders, the Women and Children to provide themſelves with ſtraw to preſerve themſelves from their Fury.</p>
            <p>In the midſt of theſe Heats, the People of this great City weary of War, began to diſtaſt the Government of the Princes, and for that Reaſon ſent ſeveral of their Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſſes to <hi>Pontoiſe</hi> where the King was, to beſeech his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty to honour his good City of <hi>Paris</hi> with his Return, which cauſed the Duke of <hi>Orleans</hi> to retire, and the Prince of <hi>Conde</hi> to Retreat, who with the Forces which he took along with him, and ſome of the Spaniſh Succors took <hi>Rhetel,</hi> and St. <hi>Menehon.</hi> Soon after the King returning to the City, attended by the Marſhal of the Hoſpital, who was Governor, the Provoſts of Merchants, and the She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffs, who had been conſtrained to abſent themſelves, was received with all the ſubmiſſion imaginable.</p>
            <p>After that the King went to the Parliament, which he united with that which he had before eſtabliſhed at <hi>Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toiſe:</hi> and in the ſame place was publiſhed an Act of O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blivion, in favour of the Rebellious, provided they deſerv'd it by returning to their Duty. But the Prince of <hi>Conde</hi> being withdrawn into the Territories of the Catholick King, marched his Army before <hi>Rhetel,</hi> of which he made himſelf Maſter, as alſo of <hi>Chaſteau Porcien,</hi> St. <hi>Menehon</hi> and <hi>de Barr.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>During theſe Troubles in <hi>Paris,</hi> the Spaniards, knowing that Marſhal <hi>de Grancy</hi> was abſent from <hi>Gravelin,</hi> beſieged the Place, and carried it, before it could be relieved.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Guien</hi> being all out of Order, by Reaſon of the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces Party, ſent for the Royal-Army Commanded by the Count of <hi>Harcourt,</hi> who retook <hi>Barbeſeux, Poudeſat,</hi> and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:46139:5"/>
               <hi>La Reole,</hi> although the Baron of <hi>Vatteville</hi> was come as far as the River of <hi>Bourdeaux,</hi> ſent by the Catholick King to the Succor of the Princes; who taking hold of the preſent op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities, ſent <hi>Don John</hi> of <hi>Auſtria</hi> before <hi>Barcellona,</hi> which was by him eaſily maſtered. Nevertheleſs this Loſs was in ſome meaſure repaired by the ſurrender of <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trond,</hi> the Fortifications whereof the Marſhal <hi>de Pallaux</hi> who Commanded at the Siege, had Order to ſlight.</p>
            <p>All this heap of misfortunes arrived to that height, that at the end of the <hi>Campaign</hi> we found the Cities of <hi>Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kirk</hi> and <hi>Caſal</hi> both reduced, the firſt by the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> the ſecond by the Duke of <hi>Mantua.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Cardinal of <hi>Retz,</hi> Coadjutor of <hi>Paris,</hi> having been Arreſted in the <hi>Loure,</hi> by the <hi>Sieur de Villequier,</hi> was car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried to <hi>Bois de Vincennes,</hi> where after he had been detain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a long time; he was removed by the Marſhal <hi>de Meil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leraye</hi> to the Caſtle of <hi>Nantes,</hi> from whence he made his eſcape in the day time, got to <hi>Belle-Iſle,</hi> and ſo to <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Year 1633. began to ſignalize it ſelf in <hi>Burgundy</hi> by the Siege of <hi>Bellgarde,</hi> which having been beſieged by the Duke of <hi>Eſpernon,</hi> Governour of the Province was conſtrained to yield to the Arms of his Majeſty notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the Reſiſtance of the Marqueſs of <hi>Bouteville,</hi> who commanded within for the Prince of <hi>Conde Rhetel, Mou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zon,</hi> and <hi>St. Menehon</hi> followed the ſame Fortune ſoon af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but the taking of <hi>Rocroy</hi> by the Prince, leſſened our rejoycings for the reſt of our good ſucceſs.</p>
            <p>Theſe ſucceſſes were attended with the reducing of <hi>Bour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deaux,</hi> and all other Towns of <hi>Guien,</hi> who had taken Arms in the Rebellion; as alſo with the accommodation made with the Prince of <hi>Conde</hi> and the Dutcheſs of <hi>Longueville,</hi> who took hold of the benefit of the Act of Oblivion. The Princeſs of <hi>Conde</hi> refuſing to accept of it, retired into <hi>Flanders</hi> together with the Duke of <hi>Anguien</hi> her ſon.</p>
            <p>The King according to the example of his Predeceſſors, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolving upon his Coronation, ſet forward for <hi>Reimes,</hi> where the Biſhops of <hi>Soiſſons,</hi> with five other Prelates received him, and at that great Ceremony, performed the Duty of the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop of that place. At the ſame time the City of <hi>Stenay</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing beſieged, was conſtrained to return to its firſt obedience, although the Prince of <hi>Conde</hi> did all he could to relieve it. Perceiving therefore that there was no avoiding the loſs, he marched all the Spaniſh Army with great expedition, and ſate
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:46139:6"/>down before <hi>Arras</hi> with thirty thouſand Men, before our Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals could put any conſiderable Succor into the Town, ſo that he had leiſure to make a Circumſallation, that ſeemed to defy all the Forces in the World. Nevertheleſs, the Terrible Lines of which it conſiſted, were ſo vigorouſly attacked by the Army which was ſent to ſuccor that place, that the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my was forced to quit his Works, which were ſufficient to have daunted any other Nation but the French, who by the ſhameful flight of the Spaniard, which happened upon St. <hi>Lewis</hi>'s day, 1654. gained ſixty pieces of Cannon, and all the Beſiegers Baggage, who 'tis very probable had all left their Bodies in their Trenches, if the Prince after he was forſaken by the Arch-Duke, and the reſt of the Spaniſh Generals, had not beſtirred himſelf after an extraordinary Manner, to make the beſt of ſuch a raſh Retreat.</p>
            <p>The Marſhal <hi>de la Ferte Senneterre,</hi> reſolving to end the Campaign with ſome honourable Action, as he had begun and continued it all the year, lead the Body which he commanded before <hi>Clermont,</hi> which he Beſiged and took, while our other Captains watched the motion of the ſcatter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Spaniſh Troops, who did nothing all the Winter but threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten <hi>Queſnoy,</hi> which was ſo abundantly revictual'd by the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſs of <hi>Chaſtelnan,</hi> aſſiſted by the Marquiſs of <hi>Montpouillan</hi> and the <hi>Chevalier de Manpeon,</hi> that that place was in a Condition not to fear the Enemy.</p>
            <p>The beginning of the year 1655. was remarkable for the deceaſe of Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the Xth. upon the 7th. of <hi>January.</hi> After whoſe Death Cardinal <hi>Chigi</hi> ſupplyed the Chair who called himſelf <hi>Alexander</hi> the ſeventh About the ſame time the Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> returned from <hi>Naples,</hi> and the Court ſent into <hi>Portugal,</hi> to purchaſe a good number of Veſſels for the Kings Service.</p>
            <p>The Enemy being at a loſs in <hi>Italy</hi> how to diſingage himſelf from the Duke of <hi>Modena</hi> in whoſe Territories the Governor of <hi>Milan,</hi> was engaged with an Army of ſix thouſand Men, and from whence he could hardly Retreat after he had loſt his Nephew, his Couſin, and above 1500 Soldiers, were at the ſame time much perplexed how to preſerve themſelves a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Genoeſes,</hi> who were become weary of the pride of that Nation, which together with their ſlackneſs of payment of the vaſt ſums owing to that Republick, was the Reaſon that they ſent an Embaſſador into <hi>France,</hi> who received all the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction imaginable from his Majeſty, to whom the <hi>Nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio,</hi> ſometime after, delivered a Letter from the Pope, wherein he returned thanks to the King for his kind inclinations and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:46139:6"/>which he ſhewed for his being exalted to the See, and withal exhorted his Majeſty to a good and ſound Peace.</p>
            <p>At that time the Concluſion of the Treaty which <hi>Cromwel</hi> and the Common-wealth of <hi>England</hi> was a thing that brought no ſmall advantage to the affairs of <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the year 1658. the Siege of <hi>Valenciennes,</hi> was raiſed by Marſhal <hi>La Ferte,</hi> whom the Enemie had put into ſome diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order. But Viſcount <hi>Turenne</hi> with his Brigade diſputed with them the Ground they had got, and took <hi>La Capelle,</hi> while they were haſtning to its Relief with a powerful Army. In <hi>Italy</hi> the Duke of <hi>Merceur</hi> beſieged <hi>Valencia,</hi> the <hi>Count de Broile</hi> was ſlain in the Approaches, and the Infantrie of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dena</hi> quite defeated by <hi>Troiti,</hi> Nevertheleſs the Duke with the remainder that was left, never forſook his Trenches till he had taken the place.</p>
            <p>The arrival of Queen <hi>Chriſtina</hi> from <hi>Sweden,</hi> and her Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception quite thorow <hi>France,</hi> ſhewed the eſteem which the King had both of her Perſon and her Dignity.</p>
            <p>The loſs of Saint <hi>Guillain</hi> was recompenſed by the taking of <hi>Montmedy,</hi> and the defeat of the ſuccors, with the Affront which the Enemy received at <hi>Calais,</hi> which they would have ſurpriz'd. St. <hi>Venant, Bourbourgh,</hi> and <hi>Mardike</hi> were reduced by Marſhal <hi>Turenne,</hi> who alſo relieved <hi>Ardres.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Forces of <hi>France</hi> being joyned with thoſe of <hi>England,</hi> vanquiſhed the Enemy at the Battel of the <hi>Downs,</hi> which was followed by the taking of <hi>Dunkirk, Bergues,</hi> St. <hi>Winox, Furnes</hi> and <hi>Dixmude,</hi> which took the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> and conſtrained <hi>Don John</hi> of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> and the Prince of <hi>Conde,</hi> to retire into the heart of <hi>Flanders,</hi> and to put themſelves under the prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of <hi>Tournay.</hi> Our Army at the ſame time took <hi>Mont-Caſſel, Graveline, Oudenard,</hi> and was alſo Maſter of the Field. <hi>Ipre</hi> was afterwards taken, and upon the defeat of the Prince of <hi>Ligne, Mencin,</hi> and other Forts, ſurrendered themſelves.</p>
            <p>The Spaniards requeſted of his Holineſs and the State of the Empire to mediate for Peace. The Journy to <hi>Lion,</hi> and the interview of their Majeſties, and their Royal. Highneſſes of <hi>Savoy</hi> could not contribute to that Agreement which was intended for a double <hi>Alliance,</hi> the Queen having other thoughts at the ſame time to make peace with <hi>Spain,</hi> and Marry the King to the <hi>Infanta.</hi> The arrival of Monſieur <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mantell</hi> was the occaſion of the Journey of <hi>Monſieur de Lionne</hi> to <hi>Moden,</hi> and they were the two Miniſters that
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:46139:7"/>treated with Cardinal <hi>Mazarine</hi> and <hi>Don Lewis de Haro.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Ceſſation of all ſorts of Hoſtility was publiſhed on both ſides, in Order to a ſolid and firm Peace. And then it was that Men began to hope for the wonted Intercourſe between the two Nations, and that the former Commerce would be eſtabliſh'd, which had been interrupted for four and twenty years together.</p>
            <p>Cardinal <hi>Mazarine</hi> and <hi>Don Lewis de Haro</hi> being arrived in the Iſland of <hi>Faiſans</hi> began the Treaty the 13th of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt</hi> which was at length concluded upon the ſeventh of <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vember,</hi> after four and twenty Conferences, at ſuch a time that Peace ſeemed to be more deſired then expected The ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of the Low Countries and thoſe of Portugal conſtrain'd the Spaniards to a Concluſion, the Queen-Mother giving them to underſtand, that if they let ſlip this Occaſion, they might probably never recover the ſame again. The diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of <hi>Marſeilles</hi> forc'd the King to take a journey into <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vence.</hi> The Duke of <hi>Merceur</hi> enter'd the City with his Sword in his hand at the Head of the Light-Horſe, to preſerve it from Plunder: which done, his Majeſty appointed the Erection of a Citadel, the place and compaſs where he immediately aſſign'd.</p>
            <p>In the year 1660. He continued his Progreſs through all <hi>Tholouſe, Bourdeaux,</hi> and <hi>Bayonne</hi> to the very Iſland of <hi>Faiſans,</hi> where happened an Interview between the two Kings, and the Reception of the <hi>Infanta.</hi> The Pomp and Conſummation of this great Mariage, appear'd extreamly advantagious to the two Nations. The Ceremonies finiſh'd, the Court return'd to <hi>Paris,</hi> which had prepar'd all things for the Magnificent En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie which the Queen made the 26th of <hi>Auguſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Death of the Duke of <hi>Orleans</hi> at <hi>Blois</hi> the 2d. of <hi>Feb.</hi> 1661. and of Cardinal <hi>Mazarine</hi> at <hi>Vineennes</hi> the 9th of <hi>March,</hi> moderated in ſome meaſure the publick rejoycings. They were very much lamented by the King and their own Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. But the Mariages of the Duke of <hi>Orleans</hi> with the Princeſs of <hi>England,</hi> and of the Prince of <hi>Florence,</hi> with <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domoiſelle D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Orleans</hi> made them forget theſe Loſſes. The re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint of the <hi>Sieur Fouqnet</hi> ſurpriz'd not only his own, but all People of buſineſs. The Erection of the Chamber of Juſtice was very diſadvantageous for them. It opened the Kings Eyes, and cauſed him to take Care of his Kingdom. It eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed an admitable Order in his Houſhold, and a rare Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline in his Armies, keeping both the great and meaner Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers in their Duty, and an entire dependency. It has alſo made him ſo much the Maſter of the Fortreſſes and Citadels in the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:46139:7"/>Kingdom, that the General and particular Governors are in a moſt perfect Obedience. The <hi>Spaniard</hi> was deſirous to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periment whether his Majeſties new Government were up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held with conſtancy and vigour. To this purpoſe the Baron of <hi>Batteville</hi> at <hi>Londou</hi> aſſaulted the <hi>Count d' Eſtrades</hi> at the publick Entry of the extraordinary embaſſador of <hi>Swedeland.</hi> The King complained thereof at <hi>Madrid,</hi> and at <hi>Bruſſels,</hi> and recall'd his Commiſſioners, that were employ'd with thoſe of <hi>Spain,</hi> for the Regulation of the Limits.</p>
            <p>The Marquiſs of <hi>Fuentas</hi> came to make his Majeſty ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, aſſuring him, that his Maſter had ſent Order to his Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors and Miniſters not to appear at all in Competition with thoſe of <hi>France,</hi> which was made in the preſence of eight Embaſſadors, and twenty two Reſidents.</p>
            <p>The Birth of the <hi>Dauphin</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> and the Prince of <hi>Spaine,</hi> the firſt and ſixth of <hi>November</hi> were great favours to both Nations.</p>
            <p>The King made ſeveral Knights the firſt day of the year 1662. There was great wondring that the Duke of <hi>Longue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ville</hi> ſhould pretend to precede the Duke of <hi>Vendoſme,</hi> who preceded in Birth, not only him, but all Forraign Princes. The <hi>Count</hi> of <hi>Soiſſons</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> refus'd the Order of Knighthood, ſaying, they would go in pairs, like the Dukes of <hi>Merceur</hi> and <hi>Beaufort,</hi> which was adjudged with great knowledg of the Cauſe in favour of the Natural Princes.</p>
            <p>The firſt Campaign of the <hi>Portugeſes</hi> aſtoniſhed <hi>Spain,</hi> as did alſo the Mariage of the King of <hi>England</hi> with the <hi>Infanta.</hi> The Succors which they obtain'd from the French and Engliſh and the Signal Victories which they got by that means have contributed much to the eſtabliſhment of that Crown.</p>
            <p>The Limits of the Kings Conqueſts were for the time hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily regulated at <hi>Mets.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Aſſault made at <hi>Rome</hi> upon the Duke of <hi>Crequi,</hi> and the evil conſequences which were thought would have follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from thence, were terminated by the Treaty of <hi>Piſa,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the year 1663. The Embaſſadors of the thirteen Cantons of <hi>Switzerland</hi> came to renew the fair Alliance betwixt them and <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There happened ſome Diſorder in <hi>Lorrain, Marſal</hi> was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſted by the <hi>Count</hi> of <hi>Guiche,</hi> but the Kings Journey in eleven days, and the ſubmiſſion of Duke <hi>Charles,</hi> who redelivered the Place to the Kings obedience, calm'd that Tempeſt. In the Month of <hi>December</hi> the King created fourteen Dukes and Peers and the Duke of <hi>Anguien</hi> eſpouſed the Princeſs Palatine, <hi>Anna</hi> of <hi>Baviera.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Germany</hi> was very much alarumed in the year 1664. at the raiſing the Siege of <hi>Caniſia,</hi> and taking the Fort of <hi>Serini,</hi> and <hi>Montecuculi,</hi> the Emperors General was, repuls'd, and his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:46139:8"/>had been loſt, had it not beeen for the French Troops un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>Count</hi> of <hi>Fueillade</hi> who defeated the Turks upon the <hi>Raab.</hi> They came to encamp before <hi>Vienna,</hi> and made an irruption into <hi>Sileſia.</hi> However that ſignal Rout conſtrained the Infidels to make a Truce for twentynine years between the two Empires, The enterpriſe of <hi>Gigeri</hi> contributed very much to it, ſo that the name of <hi>France</hi> was very much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted in the <hi>Ottaman</hi> Court.</p>
            <p>In the year 1665. The Engliſh and Hollanders made a new War and <hi>France</hi> engaged it ſelf to ſuccor the United Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, nevertheleſs he ſent the Duke of <hi>Vernueil</hi> into <hi>England</hi> to mediate a Reconciliation. But the Engliſh Treaty with the Biſhop of <hi>Munſter,</hi> very much aſtoniſhed the Hollander, ſo that the Troops that were ſent to their Releif, embroiled us with the King of <hi>Great Britain,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Death of the King of <hi>Spain</hi> which happened upon the 17th of <hi>September,</hi> was followed by that of the Duke of <hi>Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doſme,</hi> the 22th of <hi>October.</hi> The King and all the Court teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied their ſorrow to the Dutcheſs his Wife, and to the Prinees of his Family. To which purpoſe the King ſent the Duke of St. <hi>Aignan,</hi> clad all in Mourning, the Train of his outward Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment being carried up by two of his Gentlemen in Ordinary, with a ſquare Bonnet, and the Coller of the Order conduct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the <hi>Sieur Saintot,</hi> the King at Arms and the Heralds, who after they had preſented him the Holy water, he caſt it three times upon the Coffin of the deceaſed Prince, while his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Muſick ſang the Anthem <hi>de Profundis.</hi> The Count of <hi>Preſſis Pralin,</hi> and the Marquis <hi>Pluvant</hi> for the Duke of <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leans</hi> and <hi>Valois.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Queen-Mothers of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Portugal</hi> dyed, the 20th of <hi>January</hi> and 27th of <hi>February</hi> 1664. The Peace between the Biſhop of <hi>Munſter</hi> and the <hi>Hollander,</hi> occaſioned the return of our Forces. But the Hollanders puft up with their Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, affronted the Duke of <hi>Beaufort,</hi> who apprehenſive of their Treachery, gain'd <hi>Breſt</hi> in ſight of the Engliſh-Fleet.</p>
            <p>In the year 1667. The <hi>Grand Signor,</hi> who made War in <hi>Candy</hi> for ſeveral years ſent thither his Grand Vizier with a potent Army. The place was aſſaulted with great Vigor and well defended by the Marquis <hi>Ville</hi> and the <hi>Venetians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Queen of <hi>Poland</hi> dyed the 10th of <hi>May,</hi> and <hi>Alexander</hi> the VII. the 22th, to whom ſucceeded <hi>Clement</hi> the IX. who has maintain'd the Grandeur and Dignity of the Church with great Zeal and Honour.</p>
            <p>The Mariage between the Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> and <hi>Madamoiſelle d' Alencou</hi> was Conſummated the 15.</p>
            <p>The ſeveral Muſters which the King made of his Forces, were but a Divertiſement to his Enemies; but their March in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Flanders</hi> aſtoniſhed <hi>Caſtel-Rodrige,</hi> who cauſed ſeveral pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:46139:8"/>to be demoliſh'd. His Majeſty repaired <hi>Armentieres</hi> and <hi>Charle-le-Roy;</hi> forced <hi>Fournay, Bergue Furne, Liſle, Courtray Oudenarde</hi> and <hi>Aloſt;</hi> which was retaken by aſſault by the <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lander</hi> and the Marſhal-General making himſelf Maſter of the Place, cauſed it to be demoliſhed.</p>
            <p>The Empreſs being brought to Bed of an Arch-Duke, his Majeſty ſent the Marquis <hi>de Guiry</hi> to Congratulate their Imperial Majeſties at <hi>Vienna,</hi> who did not long enjoy the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs which ſhe promiſed to her ſelf of ſeeing a King of the <hi>Romans.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Eſtates and People of Portugal depoſed their King <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phonſus</hi> from the Government, and gave it to <hi>Don Pedro</hi> his Brother, who married the Queen upon the Nullity of the firſt Marriage.</p>
            <p>In the year 1668. The King having requeſted the Pope to be Godfather to his Son. <hi>Monſieur</hi> the <hi>Dauphin,</hi> he caſt his eye upon the Cardinal of <hi>Vendoſme.</hi> To him therefore he ſent full power and authority to perform the Ceremony, wherein the Cardinal behav'd himſelf with great honour. He gave the King to underſtand, that it belong'd to his Holineſs in his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and not to the Queen of <hi>England</hi> to name the Prince; and to the Biſhops to tender to his dignity and to the Holy See, thoſe reſpects and ſubmiſſions which were due. The Prince was named <hi>Lewis,</hi> and the Ceremonie was performed at St. <hi>Germains,</hi> the 24th of <hi>March.</hi> The Honours were carried by the <hi>Bourbons,</hi> and the Train of the Prince's Royal Mantle was born by the Duke of <hi>Vendoſme,</hi> having his precedence imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately after the Princes of the blood.</p>
            <p>The Diſpenſation which the Legate gave for the ſecond Marriage of the Queen of <hi>Portugal</hi> his Niece, is to be account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed one of thoſe blowes of State lucky, and unlook'd for.</p>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>Beaufort,</hi> and the Knight of <hi>Vendoſme</hi> in his thirteenth year Embarqued with an intention to make a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcent into the Spaniſh Tertitories. But the Peace and an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Tempeſt put a ſtop to the Deſigns of that great Admiral; however it made the boldneſs and fierceneſs of the young Prince to be admired.</p>
            <p>The Conqueſt of <hi>Franche Conte</hi> during the Carnival, was one of the greateſt Actions that ever were performed. it ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed all the World, and cauſed the Spaniard to quit the Name and Arms of <hi>Portugal,</hi> and their Pretentions to that Crown. However the Province was reſtored by the Peace of <hi>Aix la Chapelle,</hi> and partly at the requeſt of <hi>Clement</hi> the IX. The King having a greater regard to the good of Chriſtendome then the Grandeur of his glory and Dominion.</p>
            <p>The Birth of the <hi>Infant</hi> of <hi>Portugal</hi> happened upon the ſixth of <hi>January,</hi> 1669. at what time his Holineſs exhorted all the Princes of Chriſtendome to the Relief of <hi>Candie.</hi> The Duke
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:46139:9"/>of <hi>Beaufort,</hi> carried thither the Knight of <hi>Vendoſme,</hi> with a Detachment of Seamen. One time among the rest, hearing the Enemy beat their <hi>Reveillez</hi> betimes in the Morning, he Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded his Drums to beat a Charge, and clear the Retrench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment at the head of the firſt Battalion, which he did ſo gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly, that the Turks abandoned the Place. But the Fire which the Chriſtians put to their Magazines cauſed ſuch a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nick-Fear as forced them to return. The Duke forſaken by his own People, was euvelop'd by the Infidels. He could not quit the Field, nor the Victory which he had gotten. The Knight of <hi>Vendoſme</hi> ſtood firm to him. Fortune and War have ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that youthful <hi>Mars,</hi> and the Honour of that famous and glorious Retreat which he made the 25th of <hi>June,</hi> gave the world to underſtand he was both Soldier and Captain.</p>
            <p>The great Services which the Cardinal Duke of <hi>Vendoſme</hi> did the King and Kingdom, terminated the 6th of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> after all the pains which he had taken to forward, the Forces that were deſign'd for <hi>Condy.</hi> The Dutcheſs of <hi>Vendoſme</hi> his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, was the example and Model of Vertue and Sanctity of Liſe, and dyed this year, as alſo did the Queen of <hi>England,</hi> the one on the 8th, the other on the 10th of <hi>September.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our Monarch took a Progreſs into <hi>Flanders,</hi> 1670. to ſhew the Queen the Conqueſts lately joyned to his Dominion and confirmed by the Treaty of <hi>Aix la Chapelle.</hi> His Majeſty vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſited all the places, took a View of the Fortifications and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gazins, the ſtrength and force of his Garriſons, and what was wanting to keep them in a true Poſture of defence. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſuch has been his great pains and care, that of places mean and of no regard, they are now become of great importance and capable to endure long Sieges.</p>
            <p>A new Embroylment of the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> conſtrained the King to ſend thither the Duke of <hi>Crequi,</hi> with an Army, which took Poſſeſſion of <hi>Ponta Mouſſon,</hi> the Walls whereof were rais'd; of <hi>Eſpinal</hi> and <hi>Chate,</hi> the Garriſons of which places did but plunder and deſtroy the Country adjoyning.</p>
            <p>An Embaſſador was ſent by one of the Kings of the Coaſt of <hi>Guiny,</hi> who keeps his Court at <hi>Darda,</hi> to admire the Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deur of his Majeſties Court, and to ſee what advantages he could make by eſtabliſhing Commerce. Thoſe barbarous peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple live in Idolatry, and are very much to be pittied.</p>
            <p>In the year 1671. The <hi>Spaniards</hi> by their Emiſſaries making the <hi>Duchu</hi> apprehenſive of our Neighbourhood, and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs of the Kings Arms, engaged thoſe Republicans to forget the many Benefits which they had received from <hi>France,</hi> and to labour their own Ruine with two much heat and paſſion. To which purpoſe they ſollicited all the Soveraign Princes to joyn with them in Leagues and Treaties againſt <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Vertue and Merit of the Biſhop Duke of <hi>Laon</hi> advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:46139:9"/>him to the Cardinal Dignity. The Miniſters of <hi>Spain</hi> op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed his advancement, and the Nomination of the Queen of <hi>Portugal,</hi> which his moſt Chriſtian Majeſty very ſtifly defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. And indeed this Promotion was very honourable for <hi>France,</hi> eſpecially done to favour a Queen whoſe intereſt is much more profitable to the Kingdom.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Mariage of his Royal-Highneſs with the Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Elector <hi>Palatine</hi> was concluded; and the Articles ſigned the 6th of <hi>November</hi> 1671. and the Marſhall <hi>du Pleſſis</hi> had the charge of the Procuration for the Ceremony of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpouſals at <hi>Mets,</hi> the 16th of the ſame Month.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>France</hi> and <hi>England</hi> by the ſuccors which they gave the U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited Provinces made of that Rebellious People a Puiſſant De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mocracie. But at laſt the two Kings diſdaining their ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, joyned their Forces to chaſtize their Crime. The for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidding of Commerce, and the Injunctions laid upon their Subjects to exerciſe all Acts of Hoſtility againſt them, was publiſhed the 7th of <hi>April,</hi> and the King at the Head of an hundred and fifty thouſand men cauſed them to tremble. He preſently took from them <hi>Orſoy, Weſel, Burie</hi> and <hi>Rhineberg; Rets, Emmerick</hi> and <hi>Groll.</hi> The Count of <hi>Guiche</hi> paſſed the <hi>Rhine</hi> Swimming with two thouſand Horſe. To which dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger the Chevalier of <hi>Vendoſme</hi> was the only Prince that expoſed himſelf beſides his General. He ſo behaved himſelf, that at his firſt ſetting foot in the <hi>Betau</hi> he gained an Enſign and a Standard which he preſented to the King; and flew with the Prince to the Skirmiſh, wherein the Duke of <hi>Longueville</hi> was killed.</p>
            <p>The paſſage over this River, cauſed the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> to quit the Banks of the <hi>Iſſel,</hi> at which time <hi>Vicount Turenne</hi> cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed a detachment of ſix hundred Men to be made by the Duke of <hi>Vendoſme,</hi> which has always ſerved at the Head of his Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and particularly to open the Trenches of <hi>Arnheime.</hi> They would have alſo ſhewed their Valour at <hi>Nimmeghen;</hi> but that great General ſtopped their Fury, and beſought the King to retain them about his perſon. The Forts of <hi>Schenk, Doesburgh, Zutphen</hi> and many other Ramparts of <hi>Holland</hi> were taken in ſo ſmall a time, that there were reckoned up near fifty in two Months. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>treck</hi> refuſed Relief; on purpoſe to ſurrender it ſelf to the King. <hi>Creveceur, Coarden, Grave</hi> and <hi>Bomel</hi> were taken, and the Campaign ended with the taking of <hi>Bodengrave, Survanmerdam,</hi> and <hi>Niverberg.</hi> To requite theſe Loſſes the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> with ſix thouſand <hi>Spaniards,</hi> ſent him by <hi>Montery</hi> under the Conduct of <hi>Marcin,</hi> beſieged <hi>Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leroy,</hi> but the Count of <hi>Montal,</hi> having got into the Town, made him retreat with ſhame not only to himſelf but the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the year 1675. The <hi>Hollanders</hi> having drawn to their
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:46139:10"/>ſide the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> and the moſt part of the Princes of <hi>Germany,</hi> propoſed ſtrange <hi>Chimera</hi>'s to themſelves. But Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count <hi>Turenne</hi> conſtrained the Marquiſs of <hi>Brandenburgh</hi> to fly, and took from him the County of <hi>Mark</hi> with ſeveral pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. Whereupon <hi>Cologne</hi> was choſen for the place of Treaty.</p>
            <p>The King having cauſed <hi>Maeſtricht</hi> to be Inveſted, the Tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches were opened by Night, the 18th of <hi>June.</hi> And that place of ſuch importance, ſo well fortified, ſo well defended, was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to ſurrender at the end of the Month, a thing almoſt incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible. In ſhort, the United Provinces were ſo roughly hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led both by Sea and Land, that they acknowledg it to this hour, confeſſing that the Arms of Kings are long and ponderous, and that it was ill done, to draw upon them the Indignation of two great Monarchs; of which their Allies are not a little ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, their Countries ſtill ſuffering for it.</p>
            <p>At the beginning of the Winter, Vicount <hi>Turenne</hi> marched into <hi>Alſatia,</hi> there to fight the Enemy. The Princes of <hi>Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doſme</hi> took Poſt to be in the Action; but the Knight of <hi>Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doſme</hi> near to <hi>Mets</hi> broke his Arm, by the fall of his Horſe, that ſtumbled under him.</p>
            <p>The Campaign began betimes in <hi>Burgundy,</hi> 1674, <hi>Gray, We<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoul</hi> and ſeveral other Loſſes began a ſecond time, the Conqueſt of that Country. That which haſtned his Majeſties March, was the ſurprizal of the Prince of <hi>Fuſtenburgh,</hi> the Elector of <hi>Cologne</hi>'s Plenipotentiary. An attempt in time of Peace con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the publick Faith. For the committing of which Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in regard the Emperor gave Order againſt the Right of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, it will be an Eternal Reproach both to him and his.</p>
            <p>The King therefore compleated the Conqueſt of <hi>Franche Conte,</hi> by the taking the City and Citadel of <hi>Bezanſon, Dole, Salins</hi> and all the reſt of the Country, which he ſubdued to his Obedience, and is a ſafeguard to ſix Provinces of his Kingdom. The Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> and Count <hi>Caprara</hi> in vain attempted to Relieve it. For Vicount <hi>Turenne,</hi> with a far leſſer ſtrength gave them a ſtop beyond the <hi>Rhine,</hi> where that great Captain did wonders during the whole Campaign, having fought and won ſeveral Battels, and performed famous exploits in War. The Knight of <hi>Vendoſme</hi> was always near him, and ſtill ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperately engaged the Enemy, that he brake and diſordered the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> at the Battel of <hi>Seiren.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All this while in <hi>Holland,</hi> the Prince of <hi>Conde</hi> ſuſtained the Forces of the Empire, <hi>Spain,</hi> and the <hi>Low Countries.</hi> That Powerful Army thought to have carried all things before them and to have taken up their Winter Quarters in <hi>Picardie</hi> and <hi>Champaigne,</hi> and there to have quaffed the good Wines of <hi>Rhet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes.</hi> But the Battel of <hi>Seneff</hi> which he won from ſo many E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, was the moſt remarkable exploit of that exquiſite Captain. He thought to have vanquiſhed them at <hi>Oudenard,</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:46139:10"/>but they ſhamefully quitted the Siege. The Duke of <hi>Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doſme,</hi> who had ſignaliz'd himſelf in <hi>Burgundy,</hi> took poſt to be an Eye-witneſs of ſo great an Action.</p>
            <p>1675. The Embaſſies of Marſhall <hi>d' Eſtrees</hi> were very ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable and very bold. That of the Duke his Son was main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained with the ſame Vigour. He knew well how to let the Pope underſtand that he was obliged, not only to give audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the Miniſters of his moſt Chriſtian Majeſty, but alſo to hear their juſt Complaints, which is a prerogative that his Holineſs cannot refuſe to the firſt King in the World.</p>
            <p>The moſt important Cities of the Enemy were apprehenſive of being beſieged, at what time the King attacked <hi>Limburgh,</hi> and made himſelf Maſter of that Dutchie, which is one of the ſeventeen Provinces of the Low-Countries, which was ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned to the Government of Marſhal d' <hi>Eſtrades,</hi> After this Conqueſt his Majeſty delivered up the Charge of the Army to <hi>Monſieur</hi> the Prince, who endeavoured all he could to Fight the Enemy; But the Intentions of the <hi>Spaniards</hi> did not cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpond with the Deſigns of the Princes of <hi>Conde</hi> and <hi>Orange.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Montecuculi</hi> with all the Force of the Empire promiſed to himſelf that he would paſs the <hi>Rhine,</hi> which he did over the Bridg of <hi>Spire.</hi> But Marſhal <hi>Turenne,</hi> marching to meet him, he repaſs'd it, the Imperialiſts being very much ſurpriſed to ſee him ſo near them. The French were eager to give them Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel, although encamped among Rivers and Woods, which cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed them to follow the retreating Enemy, who to ſecure his March, planted two pieces of Cannon upon a Hill to favour his Retreat. And from thence it was that the Marſhal-Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral going to take a View of the Enemies encampment was kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with a great Shot.</p>
            <p>He had deſigned the Chevalier of <hi>Vendoſme</hi> to command the Cavalrie. However the young Duke of <hi>Beaufort</hi> was the perſon at that time, who commanded fifteen thouſand Horſe, and was preſent at the retaking of <hi>Corbi.</hi> That young Prince after ſix Campaigns, has been ſo unfortunate, that he could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver find an opportunity to fight with Honour, and ſerve the King with Renown.</p>
            <p>Upon the difference between the <hi>Count d' L' Orge,</hi> and the Marquiſs <hi>de Vaubrun,</hi> the Army deſired to be Commanded by the Duke of <hi>Vendoſme.</hi> But the two Generals being reconciled, they retreated through <hi>Wilſtelt</hi> to <hi>Althnem,</hi> where was fought a famous and memorable Battel.</p>
            <p>Upon the Intelligence which <hi>Montecuculi</hi> received, that our Baggage marched into <hi>Alſatia,</hi> he pretended to ſend certain Troops thorow <hi>Strasburgh,</hi> to Plunder it, but the Marquiſs <hi>de Vaubrun</hi> paſſed the <hi>Rhine</hi> with ſeven Battalions and twenty-two Squadrons. And indeed he had been loſt without this Stratagem. He flattered himſelf that not having to do with
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:46139:11"/>any more than one Brigade, it would be eaſie for him to be cut in pieces with a powerful Army. They fought there near ten hours. The Duke of <hi>Vendoſme</hi> at the Head of his Batta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, which appeared weak, becauſe it was not ſo numerous as the reſt, was more expoſed to the Attacks, yet as vigoruſly ſuſtained the force of the Enemy. The Enemy underſtood not that there was a Prince at the head of it, with the Officers of the Guards, and that it was the Regiment of <hi>Vendoſme,</hi> which has ever been Victorious. That young <hi>Mars</hi> outdid himſelf in a time, and upon an occaſion of ſo much danger and hazard. He received a ſlight wound croſs the Thigh, which did not at all hinder his Fighting, nor his winning of Honour.</p>
            <p>The Prince of <hi>Conde</hi> had Orders to take Charge of that Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, and leave his own to the Duke of <hi>Luxemburgh.</hi> So that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though <hi>Montecuculi</hi> beſieged <hi>Lovern</hi> and <hi>Haguenau,</hi> that great General conſtrained him to quit the Sieges and repaſs the <hi>Rhine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The defeat of Marſhal <hi>Crequi</hi> was the occaſion of the Loſs of <hi>Treves,</hi> the firſt City which the <hi>Franks</hi> took from the <hi>Gauls.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The City of <hi>Conde</hi> and <hi>Bouchain</hi> were taken by the King, the 4th. and 12th of <hi>May,</hi> 1676.</p>
            <p>The King agreed to the Mediation of <hi>England</hi> for Peace, and made ſuitable returns for the Zeal which his Majeſty of <hi>Britain</hi> had ſhewen for the Repoſe of Chriſtendome. Thereupon, Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports were agreed, and ſent where they were required, and the Duke of <hi>Vitry</hi> and the Embaſſadors <hi>Colbert</hi> and <hi>d' Avaux</hi> were ordered Plenipotentiaries for <hi>France,</hi> and ſent for <hi>Nimeghen,</hi> in Order to that Affair, which was the concluſion of Peace, ſo important and earneſtly deſired.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:46139:11"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
